<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>handsomehome.net</title>
    <link>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/</link>
    <description>Recent content on handsomehome.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>no</language>
    <copyright>© 2009–2025 Jarle Fagerheim</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2010 11:05:23 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mennesket, musikken og orgelet</title>
      <link>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/mennesket-musikken-orgelet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2010 11:05:23 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/mennesket-musikken-orgelet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prenta i Orgelspeilet, tidsskriftet for Det norske orgelselskap, nr. 1–2010.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Organistar og orgelvener i Noreg og andre land ottast gjerne for framtida. Det vert jamt betre plass i kyrkjebenkene, både til gudsteneste og orgelkonsertar. Kultursatsinga i samfunnet vert målt etter kor mange fotballbanar vi byggjer, og generasjonane som såg klassisk musikk som ein naturleg del av menneskeleg daning og samfunnsborgarskap er i ferd med å gå i grava. Er det eigentleg noko vi kan gjera? Er orgelkulturen vi held så høgt dømd til å døy?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Sound of Jørgensen&#34; på Sunnmøre</title>
      <link>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/jorgensen-sound-alesund/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 09:42:35 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/jorgensen-sound-alesund/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Denne omtala vart fyrst gjevi ut i &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.orgelselskapet.no/orgelspeilet/&#34;&gt;Orgelspeilet&lt;/a&gt;, tidsskriftet for Det norske orgelselskap.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;J. H. Jørgensens orgelfabrikk var lenge nærast synonymt med norsk orgelbygging. I alle fall hadde firmaet med adresse Bogstadvegen ry på seg som den fremste orgelverkstaden i landet. Men dei som hugsar glansperioden på mellom 1920 og 1960 vert alt færre, til liks med instrumenta frå denne tida. Utskiftinga har gått så langt at inngåande kjennskap til Jørgensen-orgel ikkje lenger er nokon samnemnar for nye generasjonar av orgelspelarar. Underskrivne er fødd etter at firmaet leverte sitt siste nye orgel, og hadde fram til nyleg berre hatt nærkontakt med instrumenta i Bodø domkyrkje og Hønefoss kyrkje. Sistnemnde gjekk som kjent tapt i brannen tidlegare i år, medan planane om nytt orgel i Bodø no er i ferd med å materialisera seg.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The new organ of Uranienborg Church, Oslo</title>
      <link>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/uranienborg-organ/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2009 09:42:35 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/uranienborg-organ/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have been experiencing something of a wave of new, sizeable pipe organs in Norway for the past decade, as several cathedrals and main churches have had their post-war instruments rebuilt or replaced. Not without reason: the 1940s to 80s are widely considered a low point of Norwegian organ building, even though there certainly are gems worthy of restoration and preservation from this period as well. This wave seems not to be affected by the economic crisis, probably because new instruments are subject to generous funding by Europe&amp;rsquo;s most affluent petroleum state.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christian Schmitt at Oslo Cathedral, October 6 2004</title>
      <link>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/christian-schmitt-2004/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2004 11:25:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://handsomehome.net/posts/musikk/christian-schmitt-2004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update (2025): This review was originally posted to the PipeChat and PIPORG-L mailing lists. Re-reading it almost 21 years later, it sounds like it was a pretty good recital. I still haven&amp;rsquo;t learned how to&#xA;appreciate modernist, atonal music, though.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-programme&#34;&gt;The Programme&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach (1685-1750): Prelude and Fugue in D major, BWV 532&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Marcel Dupre (1886-1971): Variations sur un Noël, opus 20 (1923)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thomas Daniel Schlee (1957-): Seefelder Präludium (1984)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Knut Nystedt (1915-): Le Verbe Eternel, opus 133 (1993)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Frank Zabel (1968-): Concerning Coulours (premiere performance)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Max Reger (1873-1916): Chorale Fantasia on &amp;ldquo;Wachet auf&amp;rdquo;, opus 52,2 (1900)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Last Monday, casually surfing the website of the Goethe-Institut in Oslo, I noted that the young German organist Christian Schmitt was to play a recital at Oslo Cathedral two days later. As this was the week of the Norwegian school autumn holidays, and Mr. Schmitt&amp;rsquo;s programme looked rather interesting, I decided to see if I could get a cheap train fare to Oslo that day. And so I did - huge thanks to the Norwegian State Railways for providing me with one of their 150th anniversary tickets!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
